Guide to the Annie Burr Lewis and Wilmarth Sheldon Lewis Photographs
The Lewis Walpole Library
- Annie Burr Lewis, 1903–1959; Series II; 13.73; 13 boxes
  - Albums
    - Travel album, 1928–1932 (Box 29 (Oversize))
      The album opens with the Auchincloss-Lewis wedding announcements clipped from New York newspapers followed by snapshots from wedding trips to Rio de Janeiro, Brazil, and Italy (January-March 1928), images of friends and family in Farmington, Southampton (NY), and Newport (1928), Farmington and Newport (1929), Farmington (1930), Farmington, Newport, France, and England (1931), and Farmington, Newport, Fairfield, and England (1932). The latter year includes views at Strawberry Hill, and the album concludes with a printed menu from the 1931 Johnson Club dinner at Pembroke College, Cambridge. A graphite sketch by Patty Bacon is laid in at the end of the album. The tooled leather album was made in Italy for the New York luggage firm Crouch and Fitzgerald.
    - Travel album, 1932–1938 (Box 30 (Oversize))
      The album opens with two professional photographs of the interior of the New Library (inscribed by Wilmarth Lewis: "Taken by the Metropolitan Museum 1932"), followed by snapshot photographs of friends and family in Newport, England, and Farmington (1933); Newport, Salisbury, and California (1934); Farmington, England, and Newport (1935); Farmington, Charleston, Florida, Jekyll Island, England, and Scotland (1936); Farmington, Jekyll Island, New York City (from the Queen Mary ), England, Newport, and Fairfield (1937); and Farmington, Jekyll Island, England, and Newport (1938). 1935 images include two documenting the visit of art museum directors to the Cowles House; 1936 images include six of partygoers attending Marie T. Bissell's dinner in Farmington prior to the Wadsworth Atheneum's Paper Ball; and 1938 images include views of Farmington following the great hurricane of that year.
    - Album, 1939–1948 (Box 31 (Oversize))
      The album opens with a photograph of Annie Lewis's needlepoint of Strawberry Hill, and continues with images of friends and family in Farmington, Colorado, Nevada, California, Massachusetts, Newport, and Long Island (1939); Farmington, Jekyll Island, Salisbury, Bedford, and Maine (1941); Farmington, Jekyll Island, Massachusetts, Washington, DC, Virginia, and Newport (1942-1946); Fiji, Australia, Hawaii, Farmington, and Newport (1947-1948).
    - Album, 1948–1958 (Box 32 (Oversize))
      The album opens with professional photographs of the New Library and dining room at the Cowles House; scenes in Farmington, Newport, and Massachusetts (1949); Farmington, Great Lakes cruise on the ore boat William A. Irvin, Newport, Yale Corporation, and portrait of A. Whitney Griswold (1950); Ireland, England, Farmington, Massachusetts, Newport, and Charleston (1951-1952); Farmington, England, Ireland, Newport, and Mount Vernon (1953); Farmington, Italy, Newport, Massachusetts, Vermont, New Hampshire, and the aftermath of Hurricane Carol (1954); Farmington, Ireland, England, Mount Vernon, and Newport (1955-1956); Charles C. Auchincloss dinner, with key to attendees (1956); England, Massachusetts, and Farmington (1958).
- Wilmarth and Annie Burr Lewis, 1927–1958; Series III; 0.21; 1 box
  The series holds portraits of the Lewises posing alone together.
  Series III is arranged chronologically.
  - At Newport, 1927 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - On wedding trip, 1928 (Box 7, Folder 2-3)
    Folder 3 holds a glass plate negative made in Venice; prints produced as real-photo postcards are in folder 2. Also present are film negatives from the Lewises' first stop in Rio de Janeiro, along with a paper slip used for ordering prints.
  - At Newport, 1928 (Box 23 (Oversize), Folder 15)
  - On the Europa, 1936 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - At Cowles House, 1944 (Box 23 (Oversize), Folder 16)
    In this photograph taken for Life magazine, the Lewises were posed next to their car in front of their house.
  - At Thacher School, 1947 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - At Strawberry Hill, 1951 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - In libraries at home, 1952, 1956, undated (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - In New Library, 1958 December (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Other images, 1928–1955 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    Includes portraits made in Farmington, Newport, California, England, Rio de Janeiro, and other places.
- Family and Friends, 1859–1975; Series IV; 2.33; 3 boxes
  The series includes both formal studio portraits and snapshot photographs of the Lewises' family members and friends. The folders for the couple's siblings may contain images from all stages of their lives as well as images of their children and grandchildren.
  In addition to the photographs filed here, Annie Lewis's albums (Series II, Boxes 5, 25, and 28-31) contain many pictures of Auchincloss and Lewis siblings and their children. Auchincloss and Jennings family members attending Annie Burr Jennings's Christmas costume dinners can be found in Series II (Box 4, folder 19, and Box 22, folder 13).
  Many other photographs of friends and family appear in the Cowles House guest register, A Book of Hospitalities and a Record of Guests, in the Wilmarth Sheldon Lewis Papers (LWL MSS 20), into which Annie Lewis would paste her snapshots of friends and family who came to visit the Lewises in Farmington.
  Series IV is organized into four subseries: Auchincloss Family, Lewis Family, Unidentified Family Members, and Friends.
  - Auchincloss Family
    - Family members, 1859; 1898–1966 (Box 8, Folder 1-2)
      Folder 2 holds three items: a small portrait of Esther Auchincloss in silver frame; a small portrait of Hugh Auchincloss in a mosaic frame; and an empty leather case that formerly held either a daguerreotype or an ambrotype in half-plate format. The case is inscribed on the lining paper: "Hugh Dudley Auchincloss & mother/New York 9 April 1859/9 months old."
    - Auchincloss, Emma Jennings Brewster, 1930 (Box 33 (Oversize), Folder 1)
      Emma Jennings Auchincloss (1861-1942) was the mother of Annie Burr Lewis.
    - Auchincloss Party, Colony Club, New York, 1937 December 26 (Box 20 (Oversize), Folder 5)
      Panoramic photograph with key to attendees.
    - Jennings, undated (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Jennings sisters, 1891 (Box 33 (Oversize), Folder 2)
      Emma Brewster Jennings in her wedding dress, with sister Helen (?) or Annie.
    - Nash/Dodge/Biltz families, 1899–1975 (Box 8, Folder 4-5)
      Photographs of Esther Auchincloss Nash Biltz and her children and grandchildren in the Nash, Dodge, and O'Brien families.
    - Nash, Ruth Coffin, 1941 (Box 33 (Oversize), Folder 3)
      Ruth Prentice Coffin Nash (1921-2007) was the wife of Edmund ("Ted" Nash (1918-2004).
      Photographed in her wedding dress.
  - Lewis Family
    - Album pages with family photographs, 1885–1910 (Box 20 (Oversize), Folder 6)
      Three pages from unidentified album holding portraits and snapshot photographs of the Lewis and Cook families and residences in New Hampshire and Rhode Island.
    - Danforth, Joan Lewis, 1938–1974 (Box 8, Folder 6)
      A niece of Wilmarth Lewis, Joan Maitland Lewis was the daughter of Martha Mohun Maitland and her first husband, and was adopted by Azro Lewis Jr. after his marriage to Martha in 1937.
    - Lewis, Azro Nathaniel, circa 1870-1913 (Box 8, Folder 7)
      Azro Lewis (1842-1913) was the father of Wilmarth Sheldon Lewis.
    - Lewis, Azro Nathaniel Jr. and Martha, 1900–1957 (Box 8, Folder 8)
      Azro Lewis Jr. (1883-1957) was the third of Azro Lewis's five sons, and the first born to him and his second wife Miranda Sheldon Lewis. He married Martha Mohun Maitland Lewis (1900-1983) in 1937.
      See also Series II, Box 22, folder 14, for a portrait of Azro Lewis in a Spanish costume.
    - Lewis, Charles Lux, 1899; 1960 (Box 8, Folder 9)
      Charles Lewis (1885-1969) was the fourth of Azro N. Lewis's five sons, and the third born to him and his second wife Miranda Sheldon Lewis.
    - Lewis, George Welcome, circa 1875-1932 (Box 8, Folder 10)
      George Lewis (1871-1951) was the first son born to Azro Nathaniel Lewis and his first wife Marie Antoinette Stillman.
    - Lewis, Miranda Sheldon, 1868–1922 (Box 8, Folder 11)
      Miranda Sheldon Lewis (1860-1922) was the second wife of Azro N. Lewis, and the mother of Azro, Charles, and Wilmarth Lewis.
    - Lewis, Ralph, circa 1880 (Box 8, Folder 12)
      Ralph S. Lewis (1875-1946) was the second son born to Azro Nathaniel Lewis and his first wife Marie Antoinette Stillman.
    - Lewis brothers, 1908–1939 (Box 9, Folder 1)
      Photographs of George, Azro, Charles, and Wilmarth Lewis engaged in activities together, including their 1908 camping trip in the High Sierras.
    - Other Lewis family members, circa 1897-1957 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Lewis family groups, 1884; 1960 (Box 33 (Oversize), Folder 4)
      One portrait of Lewis and Cottrell family members at the Cottrell home in 1884, and a copy photograph of Lewis, Hall, and Wiggins family members in 1894. The latter image includes Azro and Miranda Lewis with their son George, and was taken at the Wiggins home, 3412 Washington Street, San Francisco on December 24, 1894.
  - Unidentified Family Members
    - Tintypes, circa 1865-1875 (Box 9, Folder 3)
      Twenty-one ferrotype photographs, primarily groups of young women, who are presumed to be family members. Nineteen are sixth-plate tintypes. Of the two half-plate images, one features eleven women and could be a school group (one holds a rolled document), and the second shows five women with a horse and carriage, and was captured on the street outside a clapboard building. There is one photograph of a child.
    - Photographs, undated (Box 9, Folder 4-5)
      Portraits found in a box marked "family."
  - Friends
    The series hold professional portraits and snapshots of friends of the Lewises, including members of the Barney and Grummon families. Identifications were made through inscriptions on the verso by the sitter or by the Lewises.
    - Acheson, Dean and Alice, undated (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Leonard, John, 1950–1953 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - MacLeish, Archibald and Ada, 1950–1970 (Box 9, Folder 8)
      Includes color transparencies and slides taken at the MacLeish home in Conway, Massachusetts.
    - Seymour, Charles Dudley, 1931 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Stone, Lee and Charles, circa 1929-1955 (Box 9, Folder 10)
      Includes a formal portrait of Lee Stone by Arnold Genthe.
    - Other friends, 1915–1970 (Box 9, Folder 11-12)
    - Other friends, 1931–1963 (Box 33 (Oversize), Folder 5)
      Includes portraits of Dean Acheson, Max Beerbohm, Elizabeth Lee Beers, and Sir Owen Morshead.
    - Other friends at Bissell dinner prior to the Paper Ball, 1935 (Box 9, Folder 13)
      Four images of partygoers attending Marie T. Bissell's dinner in Farmington prior to the Wadsworth Atheneum's Paper Ball; they are copies of the prints found in Annie Lewis's photograph album in Box 29.
- Places, 1860–1978; Series V; 6.59; 7 boxes + 1 broadside + 1 roll
  Series V is organized in alphabetical order by state, and thereunder by city or town.
  The series contains views of houses and other locations owned or frequented by the Lewises and their relatives. The earliest images document two ancestral homes in San Francisco, but the bulk of the material pertains to the Lewises' two homes, the Cowles House in Farmington, Connecticut, and "The Castle" at Hammersmith Farm in Newport, Rhode Island. Formats include prints, negatives, color slides and transparencies, postcards, and stereo slides.
  There are several sets of views of the interiors, exteriors, and grounds of the Farmington house and its additions, taken between 1935 and 1977 by professional photographers hired both by the Lewises and by magazine publishers. There are no professional photographs of the Newport house in the collection, with the exception of a set of color stereo slides by the New York-based architectural photographer Henry S. Fullerton 3rd; the slides provide the only known images of the home's interiors. Both residences were popular subjects for Annie Lewis over many years, so scores of images of each exist in the series.
  Also present are photographs of the houses the Lewises occupied during their years in Washington, DC, and many views taken of other homes, gardens, and streets in Farmington. The series concludes with photographs taken during excursions abroad, in particular their visits to England. Many more photographs from those trips can be found in Annie Lewis's albums in Series II.
  - California
    - San Francisco
      - Jennings residence, Essex Place between First and Second streets, circa 1860 (Box 34 (Oversize))
        The Rincon Hill residence of Oliver Burr Jennings (1825-1893) and Esther Judson Goodsell Jennings (1828-1908), the grandparents of Annie Burr Lewis, from 1860 to 1861. The photograph is not signed, and is accompanied by its contemporary gilt frame labeled by the maker, Thos. Robinson of 119 Washington and 134 Sansome St., San Francisco. The Jennings family relocated to New York in 1861.
      - Lux residence, 1900 Jackson Street
        - Photographs, circa 1888 (Box 35 (Oversize), Folder 1-7)
          A set of seven photographs documenting the residence of Miranda Wilmarth Sheldon Lux (1825-1894), a maternal great-aunt of Wilmarth Lewis. The mammoth plate albumen prints are by Runnels & Stateler, and include one exterior view, five interiors (entrance hall, dining room, parlor, music room, and library), and a view taken from the house's tower looking north up Gough Street to San Francisco Bay. The parlor photograph features on an easel a portrait of Charles Lux (1828-1887), the second husband of Miranda Lux.
        - Portfolio cover, circa 1889 (Box 36 (Oversize), Folder 1)
          A piece of red velvet found with the Lux photographs; it is likely from the "red plush album" holding the Lux photographs that Charles Lewis mentioned in a June 1, 1938, letter to his brother Wilmarth.
  - Connecticut
    - Fairfield
      - Dormy House, undated (Box 10, Folder 1)
        Dormy House, on Sasco Hill Road, was the residence of Emma Brewster Jennings Auchincloss (1861-1942), the mother of Annie Lewis.
      - Sunnie-Holme, circa 1930 (Box 10, Folder 2)
        Three photographs of gardens at the summer residence of Annie Burr Jennings (1855-1939), the aunt of Annie Lewis; two of the views are by Mattie Edwards Hewitt. Also present are six printed postcards of the house and gardens, including one featuring Annie Jennings standing in her rose arbor.
    - Farmington
      - Aerial photograph, 1934 (Box 37 (Broadside))
        Plate number 6409, from the complete statewide aerial survey made by Fairchild Aerial Surveys, Inc., in April and May 1934.
      - Aerial photograph, 1951 August 6 (Box 38 (Roll))
        One from a set of images taken by Robinson Aerial Surveys, Inc., for the U.S. Department of Agriculture's Agriculture Stabilization and Marketing Service between October 1951 and June 1952.
      - Cowles House: professional photographs
        See also the album in Series II, Box 29, for photographs of the New Library taken in 1932 for the Metropolitan Museum of Art.
        - Samuel Chamberlain series, 1936 (Box 10, Folder 3)
          The date of the series is established by a letter from Annie Lewis to Moreau Delano dated May 1, 1936, that was written on a series of photographic postcards of Cowles House exteriors and interiors; in the letter Lewis writes that she had just received the cards she commissioned from Chamberlain, and is "mad about them."
          Chamberlain had photographed the Cowles House exterior for his Connecticut Tercentenary project "The American Scene," and it was used in the series of printed postcards of historic buildings found throughout the state. Annie Lewis asked Chamberlain to photograph inside the house in fall 1935 (see Annie Burr Lewis Papers, LWL MSS 21, Box 4, folder 2), and his negatives are filed here. Her letter to Delano is in the Wilmarth Sheldon Lewis Papers (LWL MSS 20), Box 33, folder 8. A second set of Chamberlain's photographic postcards is in Charles Lewis's scrapbooks (LWL MSS 20), Box 277, folder 2.
        - New Library, 1937 (Box 10, Folder 4)
          Photograph taken for The Colophon.
        - Bedrooms, circa 1940 (Box 10, Folder 5)
        - Dining Room, circa 1940 (Box 10, Folder 6)
        - Halls, circa 1940 (Box 10, Folder 7)
        - Morning Room, circa 1940 (Box 10, Folder 8)
        - Old Library, circa 1940 (Box 10, Folder 9)
        - Long Hall and side hall, 1944 (Box 10, Folder 10)
        - Stereo color slides, circa 1950 (Box 11)
          Eleven glass stereo slides with color images: five of the New Library, three of the Old Library, and three of the Morning Room; the photographer is unknown. Also in the box is the Lewises' Realist Red Button stereo slide viewer.
        - Ezra Stoller photographs, 1951 June (Box 20 (Oversize), Folder 7)
          Three mounted and signed prints of the Cowles House bearing the Stoller record numbers 143L 1-2, and 83L 1. Two are views of the front exterior and one was taken in the Morning Room. They were comissioned for Richard Pratt's article in Ladies Home Journal, and reprinted in his series of "Treasury of Early American Homes" books.
        - W. F. Miller, 1955 series
          - Dining Room, 1955 September (Box 10, Folder 11)
          - Long Hall, 1955 September (Box 10, Folder 12)
          - Main Offices, 1955 September (Box 10, Folder 13)
          - Morning Room, 1955 September (Box 10, Folder 14)
          - New Library, 1955 September (Box 10, Folder 15)
            Includes one photograph of Wilmarth Lewis in library.
          - Old Library, 1955 September (Box 10, Folder 16)
        - W. F. Miller, 1966 series
          A series of photographs commissioned for Lewis's autobiography, One Man's Education.
          - Aerial views, 1966 December (Box 10, Folder 17)
          - Exterior, west side, 1966 December (Box 10, Folder 18)
          - East Library, 1966 December (Box 10, Folder 19)
          - Front Hall, 1966 December (Box 10, Folder 20)
          - Long Hall, 1966 December (Box 10, Folder 21)
          - Morning Room, 1966 December (Box 10, Folder 22)
          - New Library, 1966 December (Box 10, Folder 23)
          - North Library, 1966 December (Box 10, Folder 24)
          - Print Room, 1966 December (Box 10, Folder 25)
        - Richard Butterfield photograph of the East Library acknowledgement wall, 1976 October (Box 10, Folder 26)
        - Meyers Studio photographs of exteriors and interiors, 1977 November (Box 10, Folder 27)
          Photographs taken for Country Life magazine.
      - Cowles House: snapshots
        Includes photographs taken by Annie Burr Lewis, and by friends and family.
        - Exterior, east (front) side, 1951-1967, undated (Box 10, Folder 28)
        - Exterior, west (back) side, 1940-1955, undated (Box 12, Folder 1)
        - Exterior, west (back) side, circa 1955 (Box 33 (Oversize), Folder 6)
        - Gardens and grounds, 1949-1967, undated (Box 12, Folder 2-3)
          Additional images appear in the slides sets filed in Other village images (Boxes 11-12).
        - Garden statues, 1958-1959, undated (Box 12, Folder 4)
          Contains photographs of the "America" and "Columbia" (or "Lady Liberty") statues after installation in the Cowles House gardens, with images of "America" prior to its move to Farmington. Also present are snapshots of the sculpture "New Life" by Mary Knollenberg, which was also installed on the grounds.
        - Interiors, 1967, undated (Box 12, Folder 5)
        - Color transparencies of house and gardens, 1949–1951 (Box 12, Folder 6)
        - Blizzards of 1961 and 1978 (Box 12, Folder 7)
      - Other village images
        Includes photographs of the Stanley-Whitman House, Congregational Church, private homes, graveyards, and village streets.
        - General views, 1943–1977 (Box 12, Folder 8)
        - Congregational Church, by Richard Butterfield, 1960 May (Box 33 (Oversize), Folder 7)
        - Color transparencies and slides
          Slide sets were kept together during processing, and therefore village images also include some views of the Cowles House and gardens.
          - Spring, 1949–1958 (Box 12, Folder 9)
          - Fall, 1949–1958 (Box 12, Folder 10)
          - Winter, 1955–1958 (Box 13, Folder 1)
          - Swans, 1959 (Box 13, Folder 2)
            Given by Grace Flandreau to Miss Porter's School in memory of Annie Lewis.
    - New Haven, Yale University
      - Scroll and Key, circa 1920 (Box 20 (Oversize), Folder 8)
        One gravure print of the Yale secret society's house on College and Wall streets.
      - Woolsey Hall, undated (Box 13, Folder 3)
        Photograph of an event, possibly a commencement ceremony.
  - District of Columbia
    - Georgetown, circa 1942 (Box 13, Folder 4)
      Snapshot photographs of the two Lewis homes in the Georgetown section of the city: a house they rented at 3201 P Street, NW, and the house they owned at 2722-2726 N Street, NW.
  - Rhode Island
    - Middletown
      Images of Alice Brayton and "Green Animals," her family's topiary garden north of Newport.
      - Photographs, slides, and transparencies, 1955, 1958, undated (Box 13, Folder 5)
      - Oversize photographs, 1950 (Box 33 (Oversize), Folder 8)
        Also present is a copy photograph of Fort Dumpling given to Annie Lewis by Alice Brayton.
    - Newport
      John Auchincloss (1810-1876) and Elizabeth Buck Auchincloss (1816-1902), the grandparents of Annie Lewis, purchased seaside property in Newport in 1852, and built a home there in 1857. When Hugh D. Auchincloss (1858-1913) and his wife Emma Jennings Auchincloss (1861-1942) inherited Hammersmith Farm, the house had been replace by a large shingle-style home (built 1888-1889). Upon Emma's death, their children divided the property. Hugh Jr. (1897-1976) acquired the main house and Annie Lewis took a smaller gambrel-roof eighteenth-century house (the Jahleel Brenton farmhouse, 1720). Known as "The Castle," it was renovated by the Lewises and they spent their summers there.
      A photograph of the 1857 house and a view of the grounds to the harbor can be found in a published memorial to Elizabeth Buck Auchincloss (under library call number 5756 Au898 902).
      - "The Castle"
        - Photographs, 1949-1970, undated (Box 13, Folder 6-7)
        - Color slides and transparencies, 1949–1958 (Box 13, Folder 8)
        - Color stereo slides, circa 1950 (Box 11)
          Twelve glass stereo slides of "The Castle": one exterior view, three views of the living room, two of the dining room, two of the library, and two each of the two bedrooms. The photographs were taken by Henry S. Fullerton of Westfield, New Jersey, an architectural photographer known for his documentation of the Kennedy White House and the work of several New York interior decorators. Also in the box is the Lewises' Realist Red Button stereo slide viewer.
      - Hammersmith Farm, 1957, 1958, undated (Box 13, Folder 9)
        Includes color transparencies and seven printed postcards with views of the house and gardens. Photographs and paintings of the gardens appeared in Country Life in America 30 (June 1916): 40-43.
      - Hurricane Carol aftermath, 1954 August (Box 13, Folder 10)
      - Other images, 1936–1952 (Box 13, Folder 11)
        Primarily documentary photographs of buildings and gravestones of historical interest; many were taken by author and architectural historian William King Covell.
  - Virginia
    - Mount Vernon, 1956, 1962, undated (Box 13, Folder 12)
      Includes color slides taken by Annie Lewis and six commercial slides purchased there.
  - Europe
    - England, Norfolk: Felbrigg Hall, 1958, undated (Box 13, Folder 13)